上溯至宇宙初始 周遭还只是一片漆黑
In the beginning, there was darkness.
不知何时 忽地一声巨响
And then... Bang!
时间空间以及物质皆由此发端
Giving birth to an endless expanding existence
此后不断膨胀 延伸 永无止境
of time, space, and matter.
每一天 新的发现都在不断为我们解开
Every day, new discoveries are unlocking
蕴藏于这里的那些神秘莫测
the mysterious, the mind-blowing,
令人大开眼界 致命的秘密
the deadly secrets of a place we call
我们称这个地方为"宇宙"
the universe.
审视地球难以置信的复杂多样性
Looking at the Earth's incredible complexity,
人类一直想要探寻其形成的原因
people have always wondered what made it all possible.
物理方程式是如何发挥作用的
What breathed fire into the equations of physics.
长期以来 宗教对此有精神阐释
Religion has long offered a spiritual explanation,
认为上帝创造了整个宇宙
that God created the universe.
目前的科学是否找到上帝存在的蛛丝马迹
But is science now starting to find elusive evidence of God
物理学能否证明我们根本就不需要造物者
or does physics tell us that no creator was necessary?
史蒂芬·霍金和我在《大设计》中写道
Stephen Hawking and I say in the book, The Grand Design,
宇宙的形成可能是一个从无到有的过程
that the universe could have come from nothing.
让我们开始在宇宙中进行对上帝的科学探索
Let's embark on a scientific search for God in the universe.
宇宙:宇宙中的上帝
整个宇宙其实非常狂暴
The universe can be a very violent place.
星系之间经常碰撞
Where galaxies routinely collide.
耗尽的恒星不断发生爆炸
And exhausted stars... explode.
但也是在这里
But it is also a place
诞生了超凡脱俗之物
that gave birth to something absolutely extraordinary,
至少地球上
at least here on Earth,
诞生了有意识情感的生命
conscious, sentient beings.
宇宙中为何会出现智慧生命的原因
It is, of course, a mystery to why the universe exists
令人难以捉摸
in such an intelligible manner,
但至少对我而言
but it suggests me at least,
宇宙 其逐渐展开的宏大计划
that there's a deep link between the universe,
以及像我们一样的生命之间有着很深的联系
the grand scheme that's unfolding, and beings like ourselves.
宇宙自知的
Somehow the universe has become self-aware.
它造出了像人类这种有思维有理解力的生命
It's engineered the emergence of comprehending, thinking beings
有能力去探索宇宙的秘密
like ourselves, who can come to know the universe.
另许多人倍感惊奇的是
Some people marvel at the fact that
宇宙拥有几百亿年的历史
the universe has over billions of years,
诞出能够领会其复杂性的生命
giving birth to beings who can appreciate its complexity.
我们现在甚至开始思索 人类从何而来
We can even ponder where and how we fit in.
但是在人类历史初期
But at the dawn of history,
人们认为自己知道此类深奥问题的答案
people thought they knew the answers to these profound questions.
古人将世界看做一个雪景球
The ancients viewed their world as a snow globe.
地球是平的 像个碟子 上面盖着天穹
It's essentially a flat earth, say a disc, covered by a dome.
英语里称作天穹
And we call this, in English, a firmament,
恒星和行星即悬在那里
and in the firmament is where all the stars and planets were hung.
所有的古代文明相信
Almost all ancient cultures believed
他们所在的宇宙都是在这样的一个弯顶下
their universe existed in a dome similar to this one.
他们从没质疑过谁是造物主的问题
And they never questioned who created it.
古人认定是上帝或者诸神
The ancients assumed that there was a God or gods
创造并维持了宇宙
responsible for the creation and the maintenance of the universe.
上帝创造了宇宙这一观点
The idea that God created the universe
直到中世纪才遭到质疑
went largely unchallenged until the Middle Ages,
当时的科学家根据他们的观察
when scientists made a sacrilegious suggestion,
提出了亵渎神明的想法
based on their observations...
宇宙的中心不是地球 而是太阳
The Sun, not the Earth, was at the center of the universe.
人类的思维模式发生了改变
There was a paradigm shift.
产生了解释我们周围自然现象的新方式
There is now another way to explain the natural occurring phenomena around us,
而这就是科学
and this is science.
从中世纪开始
Since the Middle Ages,
科学家们发展出了许多复杂的新理论
scientists have developed sophisticated new theories
以描述宇宙的宏大以及地球所处的位置
about the enormity of the universe and our place in it,
在这些理论中往往都没有上帝的立足之地
theories that often have no room for God.
许多现象曾对人类来说非常神秘
Many phenomena have appeared mysterious or miraculous or magical,
而通过科学研究
and then through the process of science,
人类慢慢开始理解这些现象
we've eventually understood them.
科学家们慢慢意识到 太阳仅仅是
Scientists gradually realized that the Sun really is just one star
巨大的星系中的一颗恒星
among a multitude of stars in a gigantic galaxy
而这个星系拥有数以亿计颗类似恒星
having hundreds of billions of such stars.
所有这一切都始于137亿年前的一次大爆炸
And all this was created in a Big Bang 13.7 billion years ago.
尽管科学理论 科学观察和实验
But while scientific theories, observations, and experiments
告诉我们人类在宇宙中的位置
tell us where we are in the cosmos,
它们仍未回答两个永恒的问题
they don't answer the eternal questions:
即人类产生的原因
Why we are here
若有造物主 它又是谁
and who, if anyone, created us.
一些物理学家继续探索这些问题的答案
So some physicists continue to search for those answers.
他们的发现十分惊人
What they're finding is extraordinary.
隐藏的非凡秩序支配着整个宇宙
A remarkable unseen order that may govern the universe.
人类为自然世界之美所倾倒
We're all struck by the beauty and majesty of the natural world, about us,
树木 天空 还有日落之美
the trees, the sky and the beauty of a sunset.
如此神奇 如此壮观
It is awesome and it's majesty.
我们如何才能了解这一切呢
How can we make sense of it all?
我们需要了解自然的潜台词
We need to look at the hidden subtext of nature,
也就是支持这个世界的数学关系
the mathematical relationships that underpin it,
形成某种影子世界
forming a sort of shadow world.
有人将其视作宇宙密码
Some people think of this as a cosmic code.
不管这些科学家是不是信仰上帝
Regardless of whether or not they believe in God,
他们大多承认宇宙密码的存在
most scientists agree the cosmic code appears to exist.
宇宙中的万物
Everything in the universe
都由自然的基本相互作用力支配着
is determined by the fundamental forces of nature.
这些作用力以数字为特征 称为
The strength of those forces are characterized by numbers, called
基本常数 它们如此敏感
"Fundamental constants" that are so sensitive
只要稍有改变
that if they changed by just a little bit,
我们所知的宇宙就不复存在了
the universe, as we know it, wouldn't be here.
譬如说 如果大爆炸之后宇宙的膨胀率
For example, if the rate of expansion of the universe right
有一万兆分之一的改变
after the Big Bang had changed by one part in a quintillion...
解释一下 1万兆就是1后面有18个零
a quintillion is one with 18 zeros after it...
宇宙将可能会持续膨胀
the universe would continue to expand...
或者坍塌回去
or collapse back on itself...
现在的一切都不复存在
And none of this would be possible.
为了说明一万兆分之一有多小
To illustrate just how small a number one part in a quintillion is,
你们可以想象一下这片沙滩上的沙粒
imagine all the grains of sand on this beach,
或者 想象地球上所有沙滩上所有的沙粒
in fact, imagine all the grains of sand in all the world's beaches.
沙粒总数大概在一万兆左右
That number's probably somewhere around a quintillion.
以此类推 假使沙粒总数代表的是
In this analogy, if all that sand represents the rate of
大爆炸之后宇宙的膨胀率
expansion of the universe right after the Big Bang,
若想破坏整个宇宙 须改变多少沙粒呢
how many grains of sand would I need to add or subtract to wreck the Universe?
仅仅一颗 一万兆分之一
Just one grain, one in a quintillion...
宇宙出现的要求就是如此分毫不差
that's how precise things had to be for us to be here.
即使这次大爆炸范围分毫不差
But even though the Big Bang was perfectly calibrated,
如果物质平均延伸至整个宇宙
intelligent life would never have formed,
智慧生命也无法形成
if matter had spread evenly across the universe.
如果完全均匀 就不会产生任何结块
Had it been perfectly smooth, then there wouldn't be any clumps,
就不可能相互吸引并形成恒星和星系
which would gravitate and form stars and galaxies.
因此在宇宙中
So, we needed slight irregularities
物质的分布要有些许不均
in the distribution of matter in the universe.
若物质分布更加均匀
Had those irregularities been much smaller,
恒星和星系就不可能形成
stars and galaxies wouldn't have formed.
若分布过于不均
Had they been much larger,
一切物质会塌缩成一个黑洞
everything would have collapsed to form black holes.
即使整个宇宙中的物质分布恰到好处
But even with the right distribution of matter throughout the universe,
没有恒星内部一系列复杂过程
life would still never have formed
生命也不会形成
without a complex series of processes inside stars
这个过程即是将氦和氢
that converted helium and hydrogen
转化成更重的元素
into heavier elements, like carbon
譬如形成所有生物的基本元素 碳
that formed the bases of all living beings.
其中一些恒星爆炸
Some of those stars explode,
为新生恒星 行星以及最终的生命
providing raw material with which to form new stars,
提供了原材料
planets, and, ultimately, life.
如果物理定律有些许不同
Had the laws of physics been a little bit different,
甚至是物理常数跟实际
or even if physical constants had been a little bit different
有些许差别
from what they really are,
核聚变的过程以及恒星爆炸
this process of nuclear fusion and the explosion of stars
都不会发生
might not have been possible,
我们也就不可能站在这讨论这个问题
and we wouldn't be here discussing it.
我从没见过任何科学家会否认
I don't know a single scientist who would disagree with the statement
这个世界无比精妙这个说法
that the world is exceedingly ingenious...
不仅是数学意义上的 不仅美丽优雅
Not just mathematical, not just beautiful, not just elegant,
这是对无与伦比之事物的完美诠释
but the manifestation of something truly extraordinary.
宇宙这种非凡的至臻之极
How could this extraordinary fine-tuning of the universe
怎能不是神圣造物主存在的确切证据呢
be anything less than unmistakable evidence of a divine creator.
人们说这种至臻之极绝对证明了
It's often said that the delicate fine-tuning
存在某种力量精心调配出这一切
must be evidence that some agency tuned it that way.
但大多数物理学家都持不同看法
Most physicists' take on this is actually not to go in that direction.
如果你再物理学中发现经过精密调整的事物
When you see something that's finely tuned in physics,
这往往意味着
it usually means there's a mechanism
有尚未知晓的机制
that you don't yet understand
在当中发挥作用
that is playing a role there.
即使看起来像是有位神圣造物主创造了宇宙
So, while it appears a divine creator planned the universe,
许多物理学家认为精密调制不能证明其存在
many physicists say apparent fine-tuning doesn't prove anything of the sort.
肯定有其它事物在起作用
Something else must be at work.
但是除了上帝 还有什么事物
But what other than God could possibly explain
能够创造出这一系列非凡的事件
the remarkable series of events
最终导致宇宙中生命的诞生
that led to the creation of life in our universe?
有种非常流行的理论 听起来似乎
One very popular contender is the idea that seems
跟有神论一样难以置信
at least as incredible as the idea of God.
称之为多宇宙论
It's the multiple-universe theory.
即在广袤的超空间中
A very large number of universes
存在数量极多的宇宙
perhaps even an infinite number,
这个数量甚至可能是无限的
could, in principle exist in a vast hyperspace.
用一杯啤酒作比喻
We can understand the idea of hyperspace
我们便能理解超空间的概念
by comparing it to a mug of beer.
这个啤酒杯代表的是超空间
The beer mug would be the hyperspace
当中的气泡就是单个的宇宙
and the bubbles would be these individual universes.
啤酒杯中的气泡外表几乎相同
The bubbles in a beer mug are all physically about the same.
设想一下 它们的属性成分可能不一样
But suppose they span a range of properties.
有一些含有碳 氧
Some of them might have carbon, oxygen
恒星和重力 其它的可能没有
and stars and gravity, and others don't.
而我们则是其中一个宇宙 富饶 复杂
We would be in one of the ones that leads to a rich, complex universe
最终诞生出生命
combinating with life as we know it.
如果真有无限的宇宙 而这种精密调配
If there are an infinite number of other universes
出现在我们所在的宇宙
the fine tuning that seems to be present in ours
与其说上帝的杰作 不如说是统计学定律
isn't an example of God's plan but rather the law of statistics.
大部分宇宙不会自然地向这方面发展
Most of these universes wouldn't naturally develop
并最终孕育出智慧生命
in ways that fostered intelligent life...
只有一小部分会
But a few, would.
因此对于我们所处宇宙的特殊性的解释是
So then the explanation for the specialness of the universe
我们是这个巨型宇宙抽奖中的赢家
is that we are winners in a gigantic cosmic lottery.
因为在不利于生命存在的宇宙中
It stands to reason that we couldn't be living and discussing this
我们无法生存并讨论这个问题
in a universe that was hostile to life,
只有生态友善型宇宙中才会产生智能生命
only the bio-friendly ones get populated with thinking beings.
多重宇宙论其实是自然和简单的结论
Having a multitude of universes is actually a simple and natural consequence
因为它和我们所处宇宙
of some of the most favorite models
诞生和早期演变的最佳模型不谋而合
for the birth and early evolution of our universe.
就像是恒星和行星
It's kind of like stars and planets.
只要有能力制造一个
As long as you have the capacity to make one,
就很容易产生更多
it's easy to make lots of them.
但是一些神学家表示多重宇宙论
But some theologians say the idea of an infinite number of universes
没有看不见的造物主论
isn't any more likely than an unseen creator
更有可能保证生命的诞生
ensuring our universe is habitable for life.
相信多重宇宙的存在
A multiverse requires as much belief
就如相信上帝一般
as belief in a transcendent God.
目前没有证据可以证明其存在
There is simply no evidence for it right now,
而且以后也可能很难找到证据
and it may be very difficult to prove it in the future.
物理学家保罗·戴维斯说
Physicist Paul Davies said,
"若只为解释我们的宇宙是如何产生
"To postulate trillions upon trillions upon trillions of universes,
就贸然假设存在亿万个宇宙
just to explain one like ours
无非是给宇宙极端加上负担"
is bringing excess baggage to cosmic extremes."
上帝创世与宇宙学说之间的辩论
This debate about the question of God and the universe
可能即将进入最激烈的时期
may soon enter an explosive phase.
令人震惊的新理论指出
Startling new theories suggest something could exist
可能有物体存在于另一维度
in an unexplored dimension
并且离我们只有几毫米的距离
just millimeters away from each person on Earth.
在宇宙中探寻上帝的热潮愈演愈烈
While the search for God in the universe heats up,
一些科学家正致力于新理论
some scientists are working to develop a theory
它被喻为 "物理界的圣杯"
that has been called "The Holy Grail of Physics".
它可以解释宇宙中的一切
A theory that could explain everything in the universe
包括它的诞生
including how it started.
这就是弦理论
It's called String Theory.
弦理论是目前流行的极有野心的新理论
String Theory is the latest ambitious popular attempt
它试图将物理界各种分支集为一体
to pull all of the disparate strands of physics together
形成统一的理论
into one grand unified theory.
既然它声称能解释物理界中几乎所有问题
Since it promises to answer nearly every question in physics,
那么弦理论是否能告诉我们
will string theory be able to tell us
到底是超然的上帝
whether it was a transcendent creator
还是物理学定律
or the laws of physics alone
创造了宇宙呢
that gave birth to the universe?
这让我们达到更深的一个层次
This is getting us one level deeper.
每当我们发现新联系时 我们就更深一步
Every time we find new links between things, we go down a level.
这令我们距全貌更近一些
It's getting us closer to the total package
最终当我们获得宇宙的所有信息时
and when we get that complete description of the universe
就无法再深入了
well, we can't do much better than that.
无论弦理论是否指向上帝
Whether or not String Theory leads us to God,
它已经指引我们去考虑
it already offers tantalizing suggestions
人类尚未发现的维度
about unexplored dimensions that humans have never detected.
弦理论的基本观点是
The basic idea of String Theory
宇宙中存在有基础能量单元
is that there are these little fundamental packages of energy.
被称之为闭合弦
You could call them little strings,
它们抖动的方式不同 而这种不同
and they vibrate in different ways, and the different modes of vibration
就产生了宇宙中
correspond to the different kinds of fundamental particles
不同的基本粒子
we observe in the universe.
根据理论
According to the theory,
这些无穷小的闭合弦
these infinitesimally small strings
是所有能量和物质的基本单位
are the fundamental building blocks of all energy and matter,
但是该理论的数学基础
but the mathematics behind the theory
却指向了一个惊人的结论
suggests one astounding conclusion.
闭合弦不仅需要在三维世界振动
The strings have to vibrate not just in the three dimensions we see,
而且需要在更高维度如此 那么问题便是
but in a larger number. And so this raises a question...
这些额外维度在哪
where are all these extra dimensions?
一些物理学家认为 额外维度可能极小
Some physicists believe those extra dimensions may be so small,
人类从未能探测到
we've never been able to detect them.
但是另外一些认为
But others say that some of them
它们可能存在于我们的宇宙之外
may lie outside our universe...
在所谓的"体宇宙"中
in a so-called "Bulk universe."
很有可能 我们的宇宙
It's quite possible that our universe,
一个四维的宇宙
the four easily observed dimensions...
只是存在于高维度体宇宙 中的一层"膜宇宙"
is like a membrane within a higher-dimensional bulk.
根据理论 高维度体宇宙
In theory, the higher dimensional bulk
可以离我们近在咫尺
could exist just millimeters away from us
因为它在另一维度
because it is in a different dimension.
但是为何它近在咫尺人类却从未察觉
But how could things exist so close to us without our knowing?
而这对于上帝
And what might that imply about
是否存在 又有何影响
the existence, or the nonexistence, of God?
天文学家劳拉·丹莉将对此做出讲解
Astronomer Laura Danly demonstrates this concept
她身处三维世界 有高度 宽度及深度
from her three-dimensional world of height, width, and depth
她将与屏幕中的
by trying to communicate with physicist
物理学家亚历克·菲力彭科交流
Alex Filippenko, who's on a television screen
他身处二维世界 只有高度和宽度
with just two dimensions... height and width.
亚历克 亚历克
Alex? Alex?
亚历克看不到劳拉 因为他处于二维空间中
Alex can't see Laura because he's trapped in two dimensions.
他缺少深度来与劳拉的世界沟通
He has no dimension of depth, that would link him to Laura's world.
他无法看见自己的身前或背后
He can't see in front of him and he can't see behind him,
因为在他的二维世界中 不存在前后
because in his two-dimensional universe, there is no in front or behind.
我却可以看到自己身后
I, on the other hand, can see behind me
以及屏幕中的亚历克
and see Alex on that screen.
她也能听见亚历克说话
And she can also hear what Alex says.
如果物理定律局限于
If the laws of physics are constrained to work
某几个维度中
in a certain number of dimensions,
那么我们就无法看到 摸到或是感受到
then we can't physically see or touch or experience
另一个与这几维度垂直的维度
a dimension that's perpendicular to those dimensions.
假设你所处的宇宙
So, for example, suppose your universe, your hypothetical universe,
是这块电视屏幕的表面
was just the surface of this television screen.
你可以上下左右运动
You can go up, down, left and right,
或者是这些方向的组合 却无法向里或向外
or any combination of those motions, but you can't go in or out.
这个维度可以用数学理论进行描述
That dimension would be a mathematical describable
但实际上却无法接触
but physically inaccessible dimension.
亚历克
Alex?
就如亚历克与劳拉身处一室
Just as Alex can be in the same room as Laura
却无法感知她一样
without being able to see or hear her,
我们身边就可能隐藏着永远无法探知的维度
there could be hidden dimensions right beside us that we can never detect.
如果上帝或其他神物存在于高维度
If God or other sanction creatures exist in a higher number of dimensions
他们便可看见我们
they might be able to see us,
并且接近我们 却不被知晓
and get very close to us without our knowing it.
你可以想象或推测 智能生物
You can imagine and speculate that there are intelligent forms
生存于这些高维度空间中
of life that live in these higher-dimensional scenarios
对我们的维度产生作用
that we see the effects of somehow in our dimensions,
而我们却没有意识到这是生物对世界的影响
and we don't realize that they're actual living agents affecting our lives.
我想现在的科学无法推翻它
I think right now science can certainly not disprove that.
它也留给了我们很多推测的空间
I think it's... it's very much in the realm of speculation.
弦理论表示我们的宇宙可能延至其它维度中
String theory predicts that our universe extends into other dimensions,
却并未说明其它维度中是否有特定生物
but doesn't predict that anything in particular lives in those other dimensions.
没有一个大胡子家伙在创造宇宙
There's no bearded fellow there creating the universe
或是操控一切
or pulling the strings.
神学家表明
Theologians argue
我们无法按照弦理论所说
we'll never find God in the 11-dimensional reality
在十一度空间中找到上帝
predicted by String Theory,
因为上帝超越了体宇宙
because he transcends the bulk universe.
藏于弦理论提出的十一度空间
Hidden within the 11 dimensions of String Theory
已经十分的不凡
is a remarkable amount of fine-tuning...
但是藏于在十一度空间中的
But hidden within the 11 dimensions of string theory
并不能完全否认
is not an unconditioned,
完全智能
completely intelligible,
无限制连续创造着的存在
unrestricted, continuously creating reality.
然而 一些科学家相信
However some scientists believe that even
即使上帝不存在于体宇宙中
if God doesn't exist in the bulk universe
大爆炸的起因可能源于体宇宙
the reason for the Big Bang, might.
有假设表示 大爆炸源于
There's one hypothesis that the Big Bang resulted
两层平行膜
when two of these parallel membranes
在高维度超空间内相互碰撞
crashed together in a higher-dimensional hyperspace.
我个人并不同意这一假设
I personally don't subscribe to that hypothesis,
但这是个有趣的想法
but it is an interesting idea.
科学如何能证明或推翻
But how can science proof or disproof what happens
在假设的维度中会发生什么
in these proposed extra dimensions
它又如何能支持或反对造物者的存在
and whether they support or undermine the existence of a creator
我们毕竟被困在三维空间之中
when we're destined to remain in our 3 dimensional world?
一种途径便是 我们可以通过粒子碰撞
One possibility is that we can find the effects of those other dimensions
试图让它们进入其他维度
by interacting with particles that may be able
以发现其他维度所产生的影响
to move into those other dimensions.
为了找到能够进入更高维度的物质
To find matter that moves into higher dimensions
科学家们建造了庞大的加速器
scientists have built enormous accelerators
用于超高速对撞亚原子
that smash subatomic particles together at tremendous speeds.
但这些粒子加速器很快就可一撞惊人
But these particle accelerators may soon do something else as astounding,
这在几年前是完全无法想象的
something that seemed impossible only a few years ago.
它们可能让科学家回溯到
They may allow scientists to go back in time
几乎是宇宙诞生的那一瞬
to nearly the moment our universe was created...
也许像一些人推测的那样
and perhaps as some have suggested,
撇一眼造物者的身影
catch a glimpse of our creator.
为确定是上帝
To help determine whether God
或是物理规律创造了宇宙
or the law of physics alone created the universe,
科学家们花了数十亿美元
scientists are using multibillion-dollar
建造粒子加速器 带他们重返
particle accelerators to take them in a journey back in time
宇宙诞生的那一瞬
to nearly the moment of creation.
为达成这一目标
To achieve this remarkable feat
物理学家在巨型椭形轨道中
physicists send subatomic particles screaming
将亚原子向相反方向发射
in opposite directions around enormous oval tracks.
当这些微物质达到接近光速时
When these tiny pieces of matter reach nearly the speed of light
科学家们将他们引向对方
scientists steer them into each other.
这样粗暴地对撞
But how can these violent explosions,
是如何使科学家回到过去
possibly allow scientists to look back
解释上帝是否存在的
far into the past to shed light on the question of God?
粒子加速器让我们超越理论的限制
What particle accelerators do is take us beyond the realm of theory
直击大爆炸之后一瞬
and give us some direct access to the physics that prevailed
所发生的事
at the first split second after the Big Bang.
这样的基本粒子高能对撞
These high-energy collisions of elementary particles
可以在瞬间产生足够的能量
that go on in these experiments create enough energy to create, for a moment,
模拟宇宙诞生初期的状况
the conditions of the very early universe,
我们可以利用物理原理
and then we can actually study that moment of creation,
来研究这一时期
using the laws of physics.
粒子对撞产生的能量
The enormous energy that comes out of these particle collisions
是大爆炸之后
is a microscopic version of the super-heated conditions
高温状态的一个缩影
that existed just after the Big Bang.
粒子加速器的一个恰当的类比
A useful analogy for what goes in a particle accelerator
就是让遥控赛车
is to actually use remote-controlled cars
在真实赛道上奔驰
going around an actual racetrack.
我现在和专家丹纳斯在赛道边上
I'm actually here at the racetrack with an expert Dana
他正教我如何使用遥控器
who's been showing me how to use these remote controls
控制车围绕赛道跑
to drive these cars around the track.
Dana 这些车速度多少
Dana, how fast are these cars going?
大约每小时40公里
They're going around 25 miles per hour.
如果是实体车 可以达到每小时200公里
And if it was a real-sized car, it would be going to 125 mph.
这是是很恰当的演示
That's actually great for a demonstration,
因为这些小物体
because having these small objects,
这些围绕轨道高速行驶的小车
the cars, going around the track at high speed
与粒子加速器里的情况相同
is exactly what goes on in the particle accelerator,
加速器中微小的基本粒子被驱动着
where you have the tiny fundamental particles begin driven around the track
以近光速的高速围绕轨道运行
at incredibly high speeds, almost the speed of light.
利用圆形轨道用强力磁场做引导
The guided rounded track, using powerful magnets.
我们用这些小车来代表
We actually want the cars to represent these super-fast particles
粒子加速器中的超高速粒子
that are going around in the particle accelerator.
现在我们已经让赛车达到预期速度了
So now that we've got the cars up to speed,
我想做一件有趣的事
I'm thinking a fun thing to do would be to
即引导它们相撞
actually guide them into each other and collide them.
可以这样做吗
Could we do that?
可以 但会是一次严重车祸
We could, but we're gonna get a big crash.
- 会发生什么呢 - 残骸乱飞
- What would happen? - Oh, parts are gonna go everywhere.
开始吧
Well, let's do it.
好极了
Oh, that's great!
残骸到处散落 我们去看看
Pieces everywhere, let's go and have a look.
好极了
This is great.
大片都在这里
Wow, we have all of these great pieces.
这里有很多碎片
A lot of pieces here.
这次碰撞产生的能量
The energy created in this collision
立刻将小车瓦解成许多碎片
immediately shatters the cars into dozens of pieces.
当这种爆炸在粒子加速器中
When this explosion is amplified exponentially,
以指数倍数放大
in a particle accelerator,
产生了如此巨大的能量
it creates so much energy that,
以至于有一刹那
for a split second,
碰撞点周围的情况
the conditions around the crash site
近似于宇宙最初形成时的状况
begin to resemble those near the moment our universe was created,
科学家或能看到上帝之手在创造这一切
and scientists may be able to see the hand of God starting it all.
宇宙早期的模样
You actually get a glimpse of
由此可略见一斑
what the universe was like very early on.
我们能看到宇宙的初生
So we get a glimpse of creation.
通过物理 我们能看到数十亿年前
We can actually see how things got the way they are now
宇宙的万物是如何发展至今日的
through physics that was going on billions of years ago.
正如通过用实验制造一些碎片
So it's as though as going back to the factory of creation
还原工厂生产的情形
by creating a little piece of it in the experiment
这使得我们能见到创世的瞬间
and allowing us to look at the creation moment
看看物理学定律能否展示当时的真实情况
and see that the laws of physics can tell us what really happened...
同样
In the same way here,
我们可以通过撞车的结果
if we look at the output of the collision,
用物理学原理推导出
and we can use the laws of physics to figure out
小车是怎样相撞的
how the cars collided
以及小车是由什么组成的
and what the cars were made of.
粒子加速器尚未能解答有神与否
Particle accelerators have not yet answered the God question,
因为最新技术还无法产生足够能量
because the latest technology can't generate enough energy
无法回溯到创世瞬间
to go all the way back to the exact moment of creation.
迄今为止 科学家们已能再现
So far, scientists have reached
创世大爆炸后的一瞬间
to a fraction of a second after the Big Bang.
尚未发现任何物理学无法解释之事
Without finding anything that can't be explained by physics.
当然 人们想回最初那一刻
Of course, people want to go back to the very first moment itself.
在他们想象中 得以见证
That's where they might imagine that one would see, so to speak,
上帝之手或是创始者之标
the hand of God or the maker's mark.
这仍未实现
We haven't got there yet.
根据我们所有的实验和观察
With all the experiments and observations that we've made,
尚未发现任何违背物理规律的情况
we've never found any single exception to physical law,
我们可以认为
so we believe that there's a good case to be made
奇迹没有发生
that miracles don't happen,
一切皆可用自然法则来解释
and everything can be explained by the laws of nature.
目前为止
Just because up to this point,
尚未发现物理学原理无法解释的事情
one has not discovered anything that couldn't be explained by a physical law
但这并不意味着 在将来
doesn't mean that in the future
不会有大量
there couldn't be literally thousands of things
用物理学无法解释的最新发现
newly discovered that aren't explained by any physical law.
为什么呢
Why is that?
因为科学本身必须接受新的发现
Because science itself must always be open to new discoveries.
然而 如果科学家最终能够
However, if scientist are eventually able
用自然规律解释一切
to use the laws of nature to explain everything,
是否有一天能用科学角度来理解
will be someday be able to understand, in scientific terms,
类似灵魂和意识 天堂和地狱的概念呢
concepts like the soul, consciousness, heaven and hell?
要求科学有一天能找到
It's probably asking too much in science to find
代表天堂或其他来自古老神话
that one day there'll be solutions of equations
这些伟大事物的方程解
that represent heaven or hell or some other great thing
似乎有些过分了
from mythological legends of old.
这些也许比科学精妙得多
It's probably going to be a lot more subtle than that.
对于创世界 科学家们希望
Physicists hope to eventually have a complete scientific explanation
最终做出完整的科学解释
for how the universe was created,
但他们说这也许超出了他们的理解
but they say it may be beyond their grasp
无法确定上帝是否创立了这些科学法则
to determine whether or not God created these scientific laws.
除非有个创造者于实行计划时
Unless we had a creator who left a message
在宇宙密码中留下了一条信息
inside the universe's cosmic code when he programmed it.
宇宙程序建筑师的线索
Are there clues to the architect of that cosmic program,
这些深藏在宇宙中的数据
buried deep within it, with all those ones and zeros,
会像造物主的标记一样
like the maker's mark
于宇宙初始时烙印在建筑师的身上吗
stamped on the architect of the universe at the outset?
这个问题充满诱惑力
Well, the problem is tantalizing those ideas,
因为就算永远研究这些数据
one might follow those ones and zeroes
也许还是找不到这个标记
forever and ever and still not find this mark.
我认为那是做无用功 注定要失败
I think that's a lost cause, a hopeless exercise,
但是在更深的层次
but in some deeper sense,
若宇宙遵循数学原理
the fact that the universe is mathematical...
当我们探索数学领域时
and when we explore Mathematical realm,
在某种意义上我们得以一窥上帝的意志
we are, in a certain sense glimpsing the mind of God.
我们真正在做的 是在一个隐性的层次
What we're really doing is exploring, at a hidden level,
探索自然规律
the order in nature.
但是最近一位世界上最受尊重的科学家
But one of the most respected scientists in the world
近期震惊了世界
recently rocked the planet
他声称已探寻出自然界的隐性规律
when he said he's explored the hidden order of nature
并用数学的证据说明
and found mathematical proof
上帝不需存在
that God doesn't need to exist.
宇宙与上帝的争论愈演愈烈
As the debate over God and the universe rages
著名物理学家霍金于其著作《大设计》写道
fame physicist Stephen Hawking said in his book the Grand Design
量子理论最新的推算
that the latest calculations in quantum theory
表明宇宙从不需要创世者
suggest a universal creator need never have existed.
霍金及其合著人伦纳德·曼罗迪诺
Hawking and co-author Leonard Mlodinow
断言物理规则
assert that the laws of physics
令整个宇宙自发形成
allow entire universes to form spontaneously.
史蒂芬·霍金和我在《大设计》中说到
Stephen Hawking and I say in The grand design
宇宙 银河系 太阳系
that the universe, the galaxy, the Solar System,
地球 岩石
the Earth, this rock,
以及所有一切事物都可无中生有
that everything could have come from nothing.
它们可以在量子论的空间中自发产生
They could have been created spontaneously from a quantum vacuum.
所以我们真的不需要上帝来创造世界
And so we don't really need God as a creator of the universe.
只需遵循物理定律就可形成
It follows from the laws of physics.
宇宙可以自发地源自于无
The universe could have formed spontaneously out of nothing,
因为根据量子论物理学
because according to quantum physics,
粒子可以凭空出现一小段时间
particles can form for a short time out of nothing,
然后再度消失
and then they disappear again.
我们在实验室观察到这种现象并测量过
We see this happening in labs. We've measured it.
也许有很多量子波动已经消逝
Well, maybe there are lots of quantum fluctuations which go away,
但某些情况便能继续发展和扩张
but in some cases conditions become conducive to further expansion.
一个巨大的宇宙便能无中生有
That can then create a giant universe out of essentially nothing.
但是菲利潘科和其他物理学家
But Filippenko and other physicists
提出我们不知道物理定律是如何或何时起源
say we don't know how or when the laws of physics originated.
这很重要
This is significant,
因为评论家们说自发创世
because critics say spontaneous creation
要求在大爆炸前就有自然规则存在
requires nature to exist prior to the Big Bang.
霍金所说的虚无
The nothingness Hawking is talking about
是一种由物理定律支配的量子真空
is a quantum vacuum ruled by physical laws.
就好比说
It's like saying,
我有一个银行账户 但不幸的是
"I have a bank account, but unfortunately
这个账户里没有钱
in my bank account I have a zero Balance."
那是否意味着
Does that mean that
我并没有在真正的银行中有真正的账户呢
I don't have a real bank account in a real bank?
当然不是
Of course not.
即便我的余额为零
Just because I have a zero balance,
这个账户确实存在于一个真实的银行
the bank account really exists in a real bank.
当神学家们谈到
When theologians talk about
宇宙起源之前已有的存在
what existed before the beginning of the universe
他们想象宇宙曾是虚空
they imagine it was a true void.
宇宙曾是虚空
The universe was really nothing,
那意味着有某物超越了宇宙
that implies something beyond the universe,
创造了宇宙
something transcending the universe created it,
将宇宙从虚无发展至有物质
to move it from nothing to something when it was nothing.
这个超常的实体就是上帝
And that transcendent entity, well, that would be God.
史蒂芬·霍金
Stephen Hawking responds
以一个令人吃惊的高雅理论予以回击
with an elegant and startling theory
可以用一个南加州的地标性建筑来说明
that can be demonstrated inside a southern California landmark.
我在洛杉矶格里菲斯天文台的
I'm walking under the planetarium dome of
天文馆圆顶下行走
Griffith Observatory in Los Angeles.
这圆顶很好地说明了
The dome gives a good illustration of one idea for the origin of the universe
宇宙起源的无边界假设论
called, "The no boundary proposal."
目前最成熟的宇宙起源论告诉我们
Our best theory for the origin of the universe tells us
宇宙源自于一个点
that the universe came from a single point.
一切物质 空间 时间 能量
All matter, space, time, energy,
甚至物理定律
and even the laws of physics
似乎都是从这个点爆发出来的
seem to have exploded into existence from that single point.
然而 当科学家们用物理基本定律
However, when scientists use the classical laws of physics
解释大爆炸是如何发生的
to figure out how the Big Bang started,
他们遭遇了
they encounter what's called
奇点
"A singularity"...
在那里物理定律似乎无效
a place where the laws of physics seem to break down
理论上必须有一个超常的上帝
and a transcendent God is theoretically
来驱动这一切
needed to start the universe.
这对科学家来说真的是个问题
This is a real problem for scientists,
但是史蒂芬·霍金
but Stephen Hawking
和其他无边界假设的支持者们
and other proponents of the "No boundary proposal"
为此找到了一个办法
have found a way around this
他们说宇宙并非始于一个奇点
by saying that the universe didn't begin in a singularity.
他们说宇宙的初始并非一个点
They say the beginning of the universe wasn't a point.
而是更像个圆顶
It was more like a dome.
大爆炸一发生 时空就扭曲到一起
Just after the Big Bang, space and time curved together.
另一点不易理解的是
As hard as it is to imagine,
霍金说时间是空间的另一个维度
Hawking says time actually started out as another dimension of space.
根据无边界假设
With the no boundary proposal,
物理定律一直有效
there was never a time when the laws of physics didn't work.
空间和时间没有边界 没有边缘
Space and time had no boundary, no edge,
没有开始 没有奇点
no beginning, no singularity...
所以试图回到宇宙初始
So trying to travel back in time to the beginning of the universe
就像试图去往北极的北边
is like trying to travel north of the north pole
或是达到比圆顶更高的地方
or, in this analogy higher than the top of our perfect dome.
无法到达 因为根本没有这样的地方
Can't get there, because no such place exists.
若沿着宇宙历史
If you trace the great story back to
回溯到你以为的最初时刻
what you thought was the first moment,
一切全都融合成了某种量子模糊
it all merges in some quantum fuzz,
所以从未存在一个起点
so there's never a singular switching on.
宇宙是自给的 这个观点很恰当
So it's a really neat idea that the universe is, somehow, self-contained.
没有以前 时间不能延伸至永恒
There was no before. Time does not extend back for all eternity.
空间和时间随宇宙诞生而诞生
Time begins with the universe. Space begins with the universe.
所以这样一来 就没有起始的一点
But in such a way that there isn't a single or first moment.
若"无边界"理论与"自然发生"论为真
If the "no boundary proposal" and spontaneous creation are true,
霍金认为
Hawking says,
宇宙并没有的起点
the universe had no true beginning
所以只需遵循物理规律发展
and would have required nothing outside
便能逐渐发展成形
the laws of physics to come into existence.
那为何我们需要超自然的造物者呢
So why do we need a transcendent creator?
不可能有个人坐在那 然后说
There was no point when someone's sitting there and going,
让宇宙诞生吧
"Let's start a universe."
根本不存在这样的时间点
You don't have that point of time anymore.
"宇宙是从无到有的" 这一理念也意味着
And the idea that the universe can come spontaneously from nothing
不需要上帝去创造一切
also means you don't need a God to make everything.
所以 结合二者来看
So, taken together, those two ideas show that
证明我们需要上帝的论点
the standard arguments for why we need a God
是站不住脚的
don't really hold.
霍金和蒙洛迪诺的评论称
Hawking and Mlodinow's critics say
"宇宙无边界"假说逻辑十分严谨
the "no boundary proposal" is an elegant theory
有可能是正确的
that may actually be correct,
但却没能直击要害
but it's beside the point.
他们没有明确说明
You're not really saying that
宇宙会无限地回缩至时间之中
the universe extends infinitely backward into time.
其首要观点
All you are saying is that
便是初始阶段一切都处于混沌状态
your initial point is a kind of fuzzy condition.
说白了
Which quite frankly means
还是存在一个起点的
you still need a beginning.
为了反驳史蒂芬·霍金
To counter Stephen Hawking
并论证上帝存在说
and support the idea of God,
许多神学家支持BGV定理
many theologians signed the Borde-Guth-Vilenkin Theorem.
它由三位杰出的主流物理学家所提出
Formulated by three prominent mainstream physicists,
阐述了"任何一个膨胀宇宙
it states that any expanding universe
必有其起源"这一观点
must have have had a beginning.
他们认为 这是真理
This is true, they say,
即使这个宇宙处于多重宇宙的环境中
even if the universe is part of a multi-verse,
只要其它宇宙也在同时膨胀
as long as those universes are also expanding.
其所展示的每个膨胀中的宇宙模型
What they showed was that every inflating universal model
定会需要引入时间的边界
would have to have a boundary to pass time.
即使这一边界将是向
And even if that boundary only indicated a transition
向新型物理学的过渡
to a new kind of physics,
即使在那个环境下 仍然需要边界
even that condition would require some kind of boundary to past time,
所以在宇宙处于虚无状态之前
so eventually you are going to get to a beginning,
终归需要一个开始
prior to which the universe was nothing,
即某种超自然的力量推动了宇宙形成
implying some sort of transcendent force to create it.
争论的两派
With each side of this debate
对于宇宙的初始和上帝的存在
citing their own complicated mathematical evidence
各执己见 各有复杂的方程
about a possible beginning and a possible creator,
究竟谁的方程式才是正确的
whose equations are right?
史蒂芬·霍金的阐述得很好
Stephen Hawking expresses this very well.
我们对于虚拟世界有各种先进的数学描述
We have all this contending mathematical descriptions of possible worlds.
究竟是什么使得其中一组方程式成立
What is it that breathes fire into one particular set of equations
从而造就了整个宇宙呢
and makes a universe form all together?
这个问题问得好
That's a good question.
究竟是什么让这些方程的成为现实
What is it that literally breathed reality into these equations
让它们发挥作用
that enabled them to do something,
使之持续升温 乃至爆炸 形成宇宙
to burn, to explode, to become a universe?
真是问到点子上了
That's a very good question,
这暗示着超自然造物主的存在
and it does imply a transcendent creator.
有关是否存在超自然的上帝
This debate about whether a transcendent God
或是物理定律使得宇宙成型的争论
or the laws of physics alone breathed fire into the universe
只有在我们找到确凿证据后才会停止
will rage until we find definitive evidence one way or the other.
但一些物理学家却提出了第三种惊人可能
But some physicists have come up with an intriguing third possibility.
听起来可能匪夷所思
As mind boggling as it sounds,
他们认为宇宙可能是由外星物种所创造
they say the universe may have been created by an alien species,
由于它过于先进 以至于人类无法察觉出来
so advanced it's become indistinguishable from nature itself.
物理学家们在寻找有关
As physicists search for answers to fundamental questions
宇宙起源解答
about the beginning of the universe
并试图解释上帝是否参与其中时
and the role a God may have played in it.
有人曾提出与先进外星文明接触后
Some wondered how this quest would change
我们现在的探索任务将如何改变
if we made contact with an advanced alien civilization.
我始终坚信 如果我们在外太空
There is no doubt in my mind that if we discovered the
追寻到了其他高等生物的踪迹
existence of other intelligent beings out there in the universe,
那将是科学探索史的巅峰
it would be the greatest scientific discovery of all time,
但同时也将不可避免地影响各大宗教体系
but it would inevitably have an impact on the world's religions,
因为这些宗教只关乎一个物种 人类
because these refer to human beings, one species,
只存于一颗星球 地球
and planet earth, one planet.
难免如此 因为宗教建立之初
Inevitably so, because the religions were put together at a time
人们只知道地球和人类
when that was all anybody knew.
先进文明外星物种是否
But would an advanced alien species
也会向迥异的神明或诸神祈祷呢
pray to an entirely different God or set of gods...
更进一步说 其科技是否已发达到
Or, more profoundly, would they have such an incredible grasp of science
能够证明所谓的神明是不存在的
that they've proven a divine consciousness does not exist?
我认为我们探测不到
I don't think we're gonna discover any surprising facts
发达外星文明的新奇信息
from an intelligent, developed alien culture,
它们和我们一样对超自然有着同等追求
because I think they're going to have the same transcendent desires that we do.
即使遇见了所谓真正存在的外星人
I'm not sure that meeting extraterrestrials, if they exist,
也未必能让我们进一步认识上帝
will give us any more insight on God.
在新旧世界对话之时 我们就是如此
We've more or less done that already when the old world met the new world,
新世界的居民所信奉的神明
and the denizens of the new world observed certain gods,
与旧世界居民所信奉的神明是不同的
and they were different from the denizens of the old world.
每每遇到新文化的撞击
Every time we encounter a new culture,
我们能从中汲取新的元素
we learn new things about that culture
感受它如何崇拜上帝 描述上帝
and how it appreciates and describes God.
但首要问题应该是
But perhaps a more pressing question
外星人是否就是人类所寻找的创世者
is whether aliens might be the God that people have been seeking,
即创造宇宙的实体
the entity that created the universe.
可以想象在遥远的将来
We can imagine the very far future
科学发展到了这个程度
where science advances to the point
人类不仅能够操控周围的物质
where we cannot just manipulate matter locally around us,
但我们能创造整个宇宙
but we could make entire universes.
我们可以根据喜好进行设计创造
We could design them and create them to our own liking.
倘若还能将自由选取物理学规律
And if this manipulation extends to choosing the laws of physics themselves,
我们甚至可以创造出前所未有的宇宙
well, we could make universes of a sort that maybe may have never existed.
我们可以自行设计和创造
We could make and design our universes.
这个想法暂且还太过空泛
Now, this is wild and speculative stuff,
但根据弦论预测 这并不十分遥远
but it's actually not so very far of what string theory predicts.
也许某天 我们真能创造出一个全新的宇宙
Perhaps we will someday be able to create a new universe,
就像是一项物理学工程项目
almost as if it was a physics project.
科学家们最终也能够
Scientist could eventually focus enough energy
全神贯注于微观世界
on a microscopically small space
在我们的宇宙创造出黑洞
to create a black hole in our universe,
那么在空间的另一边
well on the other side,
就有大爆炸创造一个新宇宙
a Big Bang would create another universe.
进一步猜想应该是这样
Well, it's just a small step from this to the speculation
也许我们的宇宙可能是由另一宇宙的
that maybe our universe is the product of a super duper intelligence
超高等生物所创造
that existed in another universe.
若这一假想是真的
If this speculation turns out to be true,
它便是古印度教义中所传授的那样
it would echo the ancient hindu teaching
世间存在着无穷个宇宙
that there are an infinite number of universes,
拥有独立的神明 幻化各自的宙宇
each with a different God, dreaming its own cosmic dream.
但这个所谓的超自然神明
But would this God be the transcendent being
会不会就是众人想象中的创世者
that many people imagine our creator is
或者仅仅是一个先进的物种
or would it simply be an advanced mortal?
母亲诞下孩子
Well, a mother creates a child and
并不意味着她就是孩子的上帝
that doesn't mean that mother is the God to that child.
我们在地球上诞生
We are all created out of the Earth.
并不意味着地球就是上帝
That doesn't mean that the Earth is God.
就算存在诸神 掌管这多重宇宙
Even if you did have multiple gods thinking of multiple universes,
在逻辑上还是应该存在某种超神
you're still going to logically have to have some super God
创造诸神
that's thinking all of the other gods
并创造诸神所掌管的宇宙
into existence along with all of the universes about which they are thinking.
当然 著名的印度教义还说道
Of course, the famous hindu teaching goes on to say
万物可能相反
that everything may be reversed
并非诸神庇佑众生
that people might not be the dreams of the gods,
亦可众生庇佑诸神
but that the gods might be the dreams of people.
这是人类正在试图探求的重要问题
This is the fundamental question that people are trying to answer.
是我们一直在憧憬这神圣秩序
Are we just dreaming about a divine order to the universe?
还是它成为我们的精神枷锁
Or is the divine order drawing us to it?
如果一项假说最终无法
Ultimately the point is if there's no way to scientifically
通过实验观察的检验
test a hypothesis through experiments and observations,
这就不能算是科学假说
it's not truly a scientific hypothesis.
因而 关于起源与创世者的问题
And so, since the question of the ultimate origin and the
基本上是无法通过实验检测出来的
ultimate creator is fundamentally an untestable question,
它就不能算是科学
it's really not part of science.
科学无法反证超越宇宙的事物
Science cannot disprove something which is beyond our universe,
其原因在于
and the reason is,
它身在宇宙之中
it's taking its data
又只能采用宇宙内部的数据
from within the universe itself.
这不等于在说
I mean that's tempt to saying,
卡通人物要用动画片中的例证
"Oh, the cartoon character is going to use data from the cartoon
去推翻漫画家的立场
to disprove the cartoonist".
这是不可能的
It just simply can't be done.
随着科学进步 上帝的能力逐步减弱
The role of God has been pushed back by the advance of science.
不过 这并不是科学与上帝之战
Nevertheless, it is not a battle between the two.
人类将一直处于对未知世界的探索阶段
I don't think there'll ever be a time when we understand everything.
世界上总会存在未解之谜
I think there'll always be the unknown.
我们也会有无能为力之处
There'll always be a frontier.
所以现阶段我们总会有
So there will always be questions that are beyond our ability to answer them
未解之事
at a current time,
但同时也有希望
but then there's always hope
我们能在未来更好的了解这些事物
that we might explain things better.
物理学和数学永远都解释不了
Physics and mathematics can never explain
定律与逻辑从何而来
where the laws or where logic came from.
因为这是一切的初始
That's where we start from, and
如果有人要说 上帝创造了万物
if people want to say, "Well, that must come from God,"
我们肯定不会去辩驳他
We certainly don't argue against that.
从某些方面来说 物理定律就像
In some ways, the laws of physics
神学家心中的上帝一般永恒不灭
are as eternal as God is to a theologian.
但我们可以想象 存在于世间
But we could imagine that there's something underpinning
维持并解释自然规律的因素
the laws of nature, upholding them, explaining them.
为什么它们是数学层面的
Why are they mathematical?
为什么它们自身性质会是这样
Why do they have the properties that they do?
为什么它们又是浅显易懂
Why are they intelligible?
上帝不一定就是问题的答案
I'm not sure God is the right answer to this,
因为上帝是文化的产物
'cause of the cultural baggage that goes with it,
我认为 就这样接受了匪夷所思之事
but I do think that accepting the universe and its underlying laws
即宇宙及其内部的定律
are package of marvels that just happens to be,
太不求甚解了
is deeply unsatisfying.
我们一定要超越自我
I think we must go beyond,
我们一定能超越自我
and I think we can go beyond.